Finding Aid for the S. Charles Lee papers LSC.1384
UCLA Library Special Collections
S. Charles Lee papers
1919-1962
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.1384
14.0 Linear Feet (28 boxes and 114 oversize boxes)
S. Charles Lee (1899-1990) graduated from Technical College, Chicago in 1918 and the Armour Institute of Technology in 1921. He relocated to Los Angeles in 1922 where he designed numerous theaters and office buildings (1927-40), developed the Los Angeles International Industrial District (1948) and built several theaters in Mexico City (1942). The Collection contains drawings, renderings, blueprints, photographs, and surveys relating to Lee's professional career including his work as a developer and the most prolific architect of art deco movie palaces in Los Angeles.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
S. Charles Lee bequest, 1990
Gift of George E. Keiter, 1990 and 1995
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942332863606533
Biography
S. Charles Lee was born in Chicago on September 5, 1899; graduated, Technical College, Chicago, 1918; senior architect, South Park Board, City of Chicago, 1918; U.S. Navy, 1918-20; graduated, Armour Institute of Technology, Art Institute of Chicago, 1921; moved to Los Angeles, 1921; opened architectural office, Los Angeles, 1922; designed and built Tower Theatre (1927), Fox Wilshire Theatre and Los Angeles Theatre (1929), Max Factor buildings, Hollywood (1931-35), Fox Florence Theatre (1931), Municipal Light, Water and Power Buildings, Los Angeles (1934-35), Bruin Theatre (1937), Tower Bowl, San Diego (1940), and built several theaters in Mexico City (1942); honored by Royal Institute of British Architects at International Exhibit of Contemporary Architects, London, 1934; began partnership with Sam Hayden, 1948; began development of Los Angeles International Airport Industrial District, 1948; established S. Charles Lee Foundation, 1962; named Vice Consul to Beverly Hills! by President of Panama, 1963; established S. Charles Lee Chair, UCLA Graduate School of Architecture and Urban Planning, 1986; died in 1990.
Biographical Narrative
Born Simeon Charles Levi in Chicago in 1899, Lee was the son of American-born parents of German-Jewish ancestry, Julius and Hattie (Stiller) Levi. Lee (who later changed his name from Levi) grew up in the Chicago of Daniel Burnham, Louis Sullivan, and Frank Lloyd Wright. Lee's own favorite building was Sullivan's Carson Pirie Scott Department Store. He also grew up with the evolving motion picture; he went to vaudeville theatres, nickolodeons,and early movie houses. A tinkerer interested in mechanical things, Lee built three motorcars as a teenager.
His interest in mechanics took him to Lake Technical High School in Chicago. He started out in architecture in 1915 by working after school in the office of Chicago architect Henry Newhouse, a family friend. Newhouse specialized in theatre design: small motion picture houses, nickolodeons and remodeling storefronts into theatres. After graduation in 1916, Lee attended Chicago Technical College, graduating with honors in 1918. His first job was as architect for the South Park Board of the City of Chicago. During World War I he enlisted in the Navy. After his discharge in 1920, he entered the Armour Institute of Technology to study architecture. The course followed the principles of the Ecole des Beaux Arts and this training is reflected in the composition and imagery of his later drawings. It is also reflected in his own emphasis on the plan as the driving force of the design. This practical approach would serve him well in his many commercial designs.
Other influences on the young architect were Sullivan's lectures in his architecture classes and Wright's work, particularly Midway Gardens and Wright's house and studio in Oak Park. Lee was also impressed by the 1922 Chicago Tribune tower competition, which juxtaposed historicism with modernism. Lee considered himself a modernist, and his career revealed both the Beaux Arts discipline and emphasis on planning and the modernist functionalism and freedom of form (Valentine, p.32). He was also a pragmatist, designing his buildings to support and enhance the commercial ventures they housed.
Scheid
3/13/2000
Chronology
1899 Born Chicago, Illinois.
1914 Built full-scale gas-powered automobile.
1915 Licensed radio operator.
[191_] Graduated Technical College, Chicago, with honors.
1918 Senior architect, South Park Board, City of Chicago.
1918-20 Served United States Navy, Great Lakes Training Station.
1921 Graduated Armour Institute of Technology, Art Institute, Chicago.
[192_] Worked in office of Rapp and Rapp, Chicago.
1921 Came to Los Angeles.
Licensed by State of Illinois to practice architecture.
1922 Opened architectural office in Los Angeles.
1920s Designed and built houses, apartment buildings, hotels.
1927 Married Miriam (Midge) Zelda Aisenstein, Los Angeles.
Designed and built Tower Theatre, Los Angeles.
1928 Daughter Constance born, Los Angeles.
Designed and built Hollywood-Western Building for Motion Picture Producers Association, Hollywood.
1929 Designed and built Fox Wilshire Theatre, Beverly Hills.
Designed and built Los Angeles Theatre, Los Angeles.
1931 Designed and built Fox Florence Theatre, Beverly Hills.
1931-35 Designed and built Max Factor Buildings, Hollywood.
1930s Designed dozens of commercial buildings and remodellings.
1934 Honored by Royal Institute of British Architects at International Exhibit of Contemporary Architects, London.
1934-35 Designed and built Municipal Light, Water and Power Buildings, Los Angeles.
1935 Licensed airplane pilot.
1935-50 Designed and built scores of small theatres throughout California and elsewhere in United States.
1937 Designed and built Bruin Theatre, Los Angeles.
1939 Designed and built Academy Theatre, Inglewood.
1940 Designed and built Twoer Bowl, San Diego.
1942 Built several theatres, Mexico City.
1948 Began partnership with Sam Hayden.
Began development of International Airport Industrial District.
1948-50s Built dozens of small factories throughout Los Angeles.
1959 Began serving on Board of Directors, Braille Institute (treasurer).
1960 Wife died, Los Angeles.
1962 Established S. Charles Lee Foundation.
1963 Named Vice Consul to Beverly Hills by President of Panama.
1966 Married Hylda Moss, Buenos Aires.
1968 Received Presidential Medal, Order of Vasco Nuñez Balboa, Panama's highest order of merit.
1974 Named Consul to Beverly Hills from Panama.
1986 Established S. Charles Lee Chair, UCLA Graduate School of Architecture and Urban Planning, Los Angeles.
Sources:
Biography of S. Charles Lee issued by Mr. Lee's office; John M. Grenner, Ed.D.
Interview with Mr. Lee, December 14, 1984
Men of California 1925-26
S. Charles Lee Collection, UCLA
Maggie Valentine, Conversations with Mr. Lee, 1984-86
Scope and Content
Collection contains drawings, renderings, blueprints, photographs, and surveys relating to the professional career of architect S. Charles Lee. Most of the collection reflects his work as a developer and the most prolific architect of art deco movie palaces in Los Angeles.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Photographs (14 Boxes).
Surveys (7 Boxes).
Negatives (7 Boxes).
Blueprints (114 Oversize boxes)
Drawings, plans, renderings (172 Oversize folders).
Arranged alphabetically by client and project name.
Related Material
The Show Started on the Sidewalk [oral history transcript] / S. Charles Lee, interviewee. UCLA Oral History Department interview, 1985-86. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
The following oral histories are available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Interview of S. Charles Lee (1987)
Interview of S. Charles Lee (1979)
Architectural drawings (visual works).; Motion picture theaters -- Design and construction.; Architecture, Modern -- 20th century -- California.; Architects -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives; Blueprints.; Photographs.
- Photographs
  - Theatres
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Perspective sketch. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Foyer. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Ladies' powder room. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Auditorium entrance. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Auditorium. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Lobby doors and box office. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Tower at night. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Facade. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Academy Theatre. - Inglewood, 1939; Art glass panel. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Admiral Theatre. - Hollywood, 1939-1940; Facade. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Admiral Theatre. - Hollywood, 1939-1940; Perspective sketch. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Alex Theatre. - Glendale, 1940; Facade, before remodel. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alex Theatre. - Glendale, 1940; Facade, after remodel. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Alhambra Theatre, 2 renderings Hoffman-Luckhaus. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alpha Theatre, No location-prototype. 1 rendering. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Alvarado Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1936; Facade before remodel. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Alvarado Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1936; Facade before remodel, with crowd. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Alvarado Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1936; Facade after remodel. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Theatre - Newhall. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Anaheim Theatre. - Anaheim., 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Arcade Theatre. - Los Angeles., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Arden Theatre. - Lynwood, 1942-1947; Foyer, art glass panel. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Arden Theatre. - Lynwood, 1942-1947; Facade night. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Arden Theatre. - Lynwood, 1942-1947; Foyer, candy counter. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Arden Theatre. - Lynwood, 1942-1947; Facade day. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Arden Theatre. - Lynwood, 1942-1947; Construction. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Avo Theatre. - Vista., 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bard's Theatre - Los Angeles. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Entrance ladies' lounge. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Candy Counter. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Auditorium. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Lee on construction site. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Foyer. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Exterior opening night. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Mural upper foyer. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Lee at opening. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Mural main foyer. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Bay Theatre. - Pacific Palisades, 1948-1949; Perspective sketch. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Berkeley Theatre - Berkeley. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Beverly Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1936; Perspective sketch. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Big Bear Theatre. - Big Bear, 1944; Perspective sketch. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bruin Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1937; Foyer. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bruin Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1937; Perspective sketch. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bruin Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1937; Floor plan. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bruin Theatre. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Bundy Theatre. - Santa Monica., 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Calco Theatre. - South Gate., ca. 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - California Theatre. (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Carlos Theatre. - San Carlos, 1939-1940; Foyer. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Carlos Theatre. - San Carlos, 1939-1940; Auditorium mural. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Carlos Theatre. - San Carlos, 1939-1940; Exterior night. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Carlos Theatre. - San Carlos, 1939-1940; Exterior day. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Carlos Theatre. - San Carlos, 1939-1940; Auditorium. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Carlos Theatre. - San Carlos, 1939-1940; Perspective sketch. (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Carmel Theatre. - Carmel., 1935 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Cavern Theatre. (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; View from balcony. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; Lounge entrance. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; Foyer fountain. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; Stair in foyer. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; Mezzanine soda fountain. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; Inside foyer. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; Outer lobby. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chapultepec Theatre. - Mexico City, 1943-1944; Proscenium. (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Construction. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Perspective sketch day. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Projection room, projectionist. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Foyer art glass panel. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Auditorium. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Foyer opening night. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Exterior gala premiere. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Perspective sketch night. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chino Theatre. - Chino, 1947; Exterior day. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Chotiner Theatre - Pasadena Project. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cinema Theatre - Los Angeles. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Crenshaw Theatre. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - De Anza Theatre. - Riverside, 1937-1939; Facade (Box 2, Folder 5)
      General note
      Streamline Moderne
    - De Anza Theatre. - Riverside, 1937-1939; Perspective sketch, Rendering of the De Anza Theatre at 123 Elm Street in Riverside, California (Box 2, Folder 5)
      The De Anza is a modest, simplified Streamline Moderne style theatre appropriate for a small city. Differences between the rendering and the exterior of the finished building show that much of the streamlining was eliminated, with the exception of the curved façade at the corner and the curved form of the pylon. The photographer, Julius Shulman, captured the new theatre in full sunlight with deep shadows; his image accentuates the dramatic black and white contrasts and the sculptural forms of the building. The gently curved blond wood-paneled walls of the auditorium and the flowing figures executed in bas relief flanking the screen carry out the Streamline Moderne theme. The curving, wood-paneled foyer displays a bas relief wood-on-wood mural depicting the arrival of Spanish explorer De Anza in California. An extravagantly curved couch, streamlined settees with curved arms and backs, and a table with curving legs furnish the ladies' lounge. The boxed chandelier susp! ended from the ceiling is typical of the Moderne taste for soft, indirect lighting. Shulman's photograph takes advantage of the strong natural light from the windows to create a study in light and shadow.
    - De Anza Theatre. - Riverside, 1937-1939; Auditorium (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - De Anza Theatre. - Riverside, 1937-1939; Lounge (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - De Anza Theatre. - Riverside, 1937-1939; Foyer (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Dinuba Theatre. - Dinuba., 1940-1941 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Disney Theatre. - Burbank, 1939-1941; Perspective sketch (Box 2, Folder 7)
      The Disney Theatre was used for private screenings on the Disney lot. Lee's concept shows a glistening exterior of shiny materials, perhaps glass or ceramic tile. To add height and presence to the building, Lee set the entrance up on a podium and accented the semi-circular Streamline Moderne façade with vertical tower forms. A broad overhanging marquee echoes the circular form of the façade; its recessed lights illuminate the glass-walled foyer and the area around the entrance.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Construction detail (Box 2, Folder 8)
      A series of snapshots taken at the construction site shows how the screen structure was framed on the ground and then tilted up using wooden wheels as fulcrums. This innovative construction technique was borrowed from concrete tilt-slab construction pioneered in Southern California in the early part of the century by Irving Gill and later used by other Southern California modernists.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Sign (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Lee gave the sign (4) a Streamline Moderne look, but the screen structure (5) itself is almost completely utilitarian.
    - Drive-in Theatres - Ventura, Perspective sketch (Box 2, Folder 8)
      This earliest-known concept for a Drive-in theater by Lee, the Ventura Drive-In, shows a sophisticated use of illuminated triangular forms massed alongside the large illuminated screen structure and along the edges of the parking lot, creating an advertising sign for the theater out of the Drive-in form itself. The sharp-edged forms are clearly Art Deco in character, a style that is sometimes called Zig-Zag Moderne. The design vocabulary was adapted from usage current in theatre design at the time. A note on the back of the print reads: Original Conception Drive-In Plans Completed - Project not constructed.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Construction (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Drive-in Theatres. - San Diego, 1948; Screen, parking view (Box 2, Folder 8)
      This view of the screen shows the typical Drive-in parking lot and speaker stanchions. The wings flanking the projection screen were built to deflect light from passing cars and also to obstruct the view of the screen from non-paying viewers outside the parking lot.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Construction (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Construction (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Construction (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Construction (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Drive-in Theatres. - San Diego, 1948; Sign (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Snapshot view of the El Rancho Drive-In sign.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - San Diego, 1948; Screen, street view (Box 2, Folder 8)
      The Rancho Drive-In in San Diego was built in the same year (1948) as the Edwards Drive-In in Arcadia. Although no construction photos survive, the construction technique was presumably similar. In this example, Lee used the street side of the screen structure to feature a colorful mural-like scene of the Mexican landscape illuminated from behind, a cultural reference appropriate to the border city of San Diego.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Screen, parking view (Box 2, Folder 8)
      This view of the screen (7) from the parking lot shows the angled parking bays and speaker posts.
    - Drive-in Theatres - El Monte, Aerial view (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Drive-in theatre, El Monte, California. Aerial view.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Screen, pylon sign from street (Box 2, Folder 8)
      The completed theater (3) relies on a monumental sign perpendicular to the screen structure to attract customers.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Bird's-eye rendering (Box 2, Folder 8)
      The Drive-in theatre concept was first tried in the mid-1930s, but only after World War II did the idea gain widespread acceptance. Lee designed several Drive-in theaters, a type especially suited to the mild climate and car-dependent economy of Southern California. The Drive-in allowed the whole family to go to the movies in the family car, with no need for a baby-sitter. It also proved especially popular with dating teen-agers, who found Drive-ins the ideal refuge from watchful adult eyes. The Drive-in was also cheap to build. A large piece of land, a structure to display the screen and smaller buildings for tickets, refreshments and the projector were all that was needed. The parking lot was usually graded to provide the parked cars with a good angle for viewing the screen, and each space was equipped with a speaker that could be hooked to the dashboard to bring the sound into the car.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Perspective sketch (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Lee's renderings for the Edwards Drive-In in Arcadia (1948) show both a perspective plan (1) and a perspective from the road (2). The theater was planned in conjunction with Arcadia's Royal Oaks subdivision, hence the image of the oak and the reference to oaks in the original scheme.
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Screen, street view (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Drive-in Theatres. - Arcadia, 1948; Structure detail (Box 2, Folder 8)
      To give the screen structure a more substantial-looking base, Lee designed a series of tall ladder-like structures (6) that he covered with translucent corrugated plastic panels. This structure may have been illuminated from within at night to attract customers.
    - Egyptian Theatre. - Long Beach?, 1936; Perspective sketch (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Lee's concept rendering for a storefront theatre in the popular Egyptian theme betrays little attention on the façade to Egyptian-derived elements. The tall pylon sign, the illuminated marque extended out over the sidewalk, and the dramatically curved forms all serve to advertise the product to the audience on the street.
    - Follies Theatre, Foyer (Box 2, Folder 10)
      The foyer was a small cramped space, used only for collecting tickets.
    - Follies Theatre, Auditorium, boxes (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Box seats were also available at the sides of the main or orchestra level.
    - Follies Theatre, Lobby entrance (Box 2, Folder 10)
      The Lee collection contains a number of photographs of theatres that Lee was charged with remodeling. This series of photos of a turn-of-the-century vaudeville theatre illustrates, by contrast, the innovations developed by architects for motion picture theatres. The entry to these older theatres was often off the street, through a long hallway. Advertising displays were merely cardboard signs.
    - Follies Theatre, Auditorium, balcony (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Traditional-style chandeliers hung from the ceiling.
    - Follies Theatre, Auditorium, proscenium (Box 2, Folder 10)
      All design attention and expense were focused on the elaborate Beaux Arts-style auditorium, which featured a proscenium flanked by protruding boxes.
    - Fox Florence Theatre. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Auditorium, proscenium (Box 2, Folder 12)
      The Beaux Arts style interior features a proscenium arch framed by pseudo quoins and flanked by giant compositions of paired columns centered by oversize sculptures and cartouches. There is clearly a stage behind the curtain and the organ used to accompany silent motion pictures is seen at the lower left. The perforated panel in the center of the ceiling is a ventilation vent.
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Facade (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Lee designed an elegant Beaux Arts style theatre to be used both for legitimate stage shows and motion pictures for the Southern California beach city, Long Beach. The massive poured-concrete building with its monumental cornice centered by a giant cartouche dominated the urban landscape of downtown Long Beach. The retail shop fronts at street level give a sense of the scale of the building.
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Auditorium, lantern (Box 2, Folder 12)